[Música]
>> Bienvenidos de nuevo, personas.
Muchas gracias por estar con nosotros . Esperamos que todos hayan disfrutado
su descanso para comer y empezar rejuvenecido y renovado y listo para
seguir con tres o cuatro más módulos en relación con la consulta SQL Server 2012.
Todavía estoy en el estudio con Tobias. Él no la fianza en mí durante
el descanso para comer. Bienvenidos de nuevo, señor. Muchas gracias por estar
con nosotros hoy.
>> Gracias. Y sobre todo, gracias a todos los que estan donde
es las 2:00 a.m. en este momento.
>> Si, exacto. Contamos con que sea fácil en donde estemos. Así que vamos a
repasar lo que hemos pasado hasta ahora. Pasamos por la clase
de la que acaba de presentar algunas de las declaraciones y los elementos básicos
que están involucrados con SQL Server. Pasamos un poco de tiempo
en eso y hablando un poco acerca de la sentencia select básico.
Fuimos en el módulo, miramos las instrucciones select avanzada,
realmente acaba de presentar algunas de las cláusulas allí como distinto y
el caso de la función escalar, la articulación, fusionar. Se mostró cómo filtrar
y ordenar los datos. A continuación, pasamos a los tipos de datos. Hablando de los
diferentes tipos de tipos de datos, la hora y fecha son tipos de datos y
los tipos de datos de caracteres y algunas funciones asociadas con los
tipos de datos que nos permite ser creativo con la forma en las que se muestran
y lo que podemos hacer con los tipos de datos. Luego hablamos de
agrupación y agregación de datos. No debe confundirse con agravantes.
Y hablamos de algunas de las funciones de agregado como por
el grupo que tienen. Algunas de las sub consultas disponibles para nosotros
y un par de demos realmente buenos de Tobias en las vistas, las
diferentes tablas, tablas derivadas y las diferentes maneras en que podría
trabajar con ese contenido. Luego tomamos un descanso para comer de 60 minutos, que
es muy bonito, pero ahora tenemos que avanzar de nuevo en algún contenido.
Vamos a entrar en el módulo 5 en la que tratamos operadores de conjunto
y hablar de algunas ventanas adicionales de funciones y agrupación
maneras opcionales para nosotros de nuevo resumen de algunos datos. Hablaremos
sobre conjunto de operadores, ventanas de funciones, conjuntos de agrupación utilizando cosas
como pivotes y cubos y roll-ups eso es lo que vamos a adentrar
aquí en esta sección. Tenemos algunas cosas interesantes que nos queda por
discutir. Así que vamos a abrir esta sección con operadores de conjuntos.
Es una interaccion entre conjuntos. Es el resultado de dos entradas
consultas que se pueden ya sea combinar, operando en contra o incluso en comparación.
Ambos tienen que tener columnas compatibles, mismo número de columnas.
No se puede utilizar la cláusula ORDER BY allí cuando usted está buscando en
estas consultas de entrada. Los que se consideran iguales cuando usted está comparando conjuntos.
Y algunos de estos operadores conjunto incluyen uniones e intersecciones,
intersectar y con excepción y aplicar.
El operador de unión no hablamos un poco acerca de este Tobias
un poco antes.
>> Creo que hicimos.
>> No hay nada nuevo aquí, tuvimos una gran demostración de Tobias en esto.
Combinar el contenido de diferentes tablas y ponerlo en un solo
conjunto resultante.
Sólo tendremos que ir por esta causa que ya ha visto una demostración fresca
en esto. De hecho, él utiliza una unión de todas las declaraciones. Él mostró
la diferencia entre la unión, unión de todo. He aquí una muestra de declaración
de cómo se llevaría a cabo en caso de que usted no estaba
capaz de seguir o que se alejó al baño.
Ahora vamos a introducir un nuevo llamado el operador de intersección.
Esto sólo devuelve las filas distintas que aparecen en ambos conjuntos de resultados.
Qué significa eso para mí Tobias.
>> Esto significa que si usted tiene una lista de, por ejemplo, los empleados y
una lista de los clientes por su nombre es posible que desee ver, además, que si
estas personas son clientes y empleados.
>> Muy bien.
>> Como un ejemplo. Cuando se usaría intersecta. Le da la
intersección entre los conjuntos.
>> Todo bien. Bonito. Así que eso es muy bueno para poder
tomar esos contenidos a partir de dos tablas diferentes y ser capaz de llevar
de nuevo en un único conjunto de resultados. La excepción que el operador devuelve
sólo roles distintos que aparecen en el conjunto de la izquierda. Recuerde que si
hablamos izquierda estamos hablando de la primera parte de la consulta
pero no conjunto el derecho. Tiene sentido.
>> Si se toma el ejemplo anterior me mostrara todos los clientes que están
no también empleados.
>> No también empleados. Un pequeño giro diferente. Pero dónde
usando las mismas tablas. Estamos utilizando posiblemente las mismas columnas
pero estamos accediendo los mismos datos, pero es un conjunto de resultados diferentes
que queremos trabajar.
A continuación, presentamos el operador de aplicacion, que es un operador que se utiliza
en la cláusula from. Puede ser cualquiera aplicacion transversal o aplicacion exterior.
Su aplicacion exterior se aplica a la expresión de tabla derecha.
Para cada fila de la tabla de la izquierda. Y la aplicacion externa también añade
filas para los que no tienen columnas para la tabla de la derecha. Hay un
ejemplo en el que se desea utilizar un operador de aplicacion cuando
hablan sobre las tablas entre el empleado y el cliente o no
Tenemos un ejemplo ... Tengo uno aquí que es una especie de lista
que podemos seleccionar la lista de columnas de la tabla de la izquierda.
Teniendo en cuenta que A nombre de la lista que podemos hacer cruzada o exterior y aplicacion a continuación, utilizar
expresiones de tabla derivados que hablamos anteriormente o en expresiones de línea.
>> Puede mostrar una demo sencilla.
Así que en este caso vamos a decir lo que quiero mostrar es cada ...
todos los clientes y los cinco últimos pedidos de cada cliente.
Y usted puede hacer esto de muchas maneras diferentes, pero uno está usando aplicacion.
Así que digamos que estamos seleccionando de sales.customer
como un ejemplo. Estamos agarrando ID de cliente.
Y número de cuenta. Ahora quiero seguir adelante y tomar los pedidos.
Si yo simplemente hago una unión, no hay manera para mí decir sólo dame
los cinco últimos pedidos.
De ninguna manera es una declaración fuerte. Para que pueda seguir adelante y utilizar la
función de operador fila de uso, para llevar a cabo básicamente cosas similares.
Pero digamos que yo quiero hacer lo aplicacion.
Quieres usar aplicacion en este caso. Ahora sólo puedo decir aplicar y
dame los cinco
mejores pedidos, ventas cabecera de la orden aquí. Hay ... y la cosa
con aplicacion ahora es ejecutado una vez por cada fila del conjunto exterior.
Así que ahora, una vez por cada cliente que se aplica a cualquiera que sea la carga de trabajo
tenemos. Así que vamos a decir que tenemos ID de territorio es igual a tres
como un ejemplo. Así que aquí ahora agarrar todos los pedidos que el cliente
ID es el cliente estoy. Muy bien. Y también puedo decir aquí por orden ...
Puedo utilizar el orden de en esta tabla derivada simplemente porque estoy usando
los mejores operadores. Asi que ordena por, fecha de la orden, descendiendo. Yo obtengo
los cinco últimos pedidos. Y déjame agarrar lo que necesito.
Digamos que yo quiero la fecha del pedido y justo el ID de Orden.
Y voy a llamar a este conjunto O. Así que ahora sólo puedo decir dame esta
del cliente y de estas columnas de orden. Y la diferencia
entre la aplicacion de cruz y la aplicacion exterior es aproximadamente la misma que entre
su union y union externa, lo que significa que en la aplicacion de cruz sólo voy a conseguir
clientes que ahora tienen al menos un pedido. Entonces dónde la interior
consulta devuelve al menos una fila y aplicacion exterior me daría
cuando no tienen ningún pedido. Así que voy a ir con eso.
Y ahí vamos. Así que todos estos primeros aparentemente no haga
tener cualquier orden y como nos desplazamos hacia abajo empezamos la búsqueda de un par
de ellos con órdenes. Como se puede ver aquí, yo estoy poniendo cuatro filas
una copia de este mismo cliente, ya que al parecer cliente
pasó a tener cinco órdenes. Así que estamos mostrando hasta los cinco
últimos pedidos de ese cliente.
>> Gotcha. Bueno. Increíble. Así que este es otro uso, de otra manera
para que nosotros examinemos minuciosamente su contenido y entrar con personalizado
conjunto de resultados que es lo que todo esto ha sido acerca de, más o menos,
es lo que tenemos todos estos datos por ahí ... hay tantos
maneras para mí para que me quieren rebanar y producir un conjunto de resultados
eso me va a dar exactamente lo que necesito para generar es la
información y suministrar la información al respecto a la gestión
lo que está pasando con un empleado en particular o un cliente o un vendedor.
Así que esa es una manera de examinar minuciosamente el contenido a ser capaz de obtener
a esos datos y dar como resultado un conjunto de resultados que alcanza las necesidades que
tu tenias.
Así que vamos a pasar a la próxima sección, que es las funciones de Windows.
Tenemos algunas funciones de Windows. Introducimos brevemente una par ya.
Tobias hizo una gran demostración en uno antes, y dentro de Aquí vamos a
mirar en ventanas de SQL que se extiende el T es igual al enfoque basado en el conjunto.
Hemos estado hablando acerca de los operadores establecidos. Ellos le permiten especificar
una orden como parte de un cálculo.
Permiten la separación y la formulación de las filas para apoyar ciertaa
funciones y que pueden simplificar las consultas mediante la ejecución de los totales o
los promedios móviles o tal vez incluso la falta de datos. Estamos tratando de
encontrar cuando hubo una pausa en un entorno de ventas o algo así.
Así que la idea de ventanas o partición de particionamiento limita conjuntos
a las filas de los mismos valores en lo que se llama una columna de partición.
Utilizamos la partición por la declaración en una cláusula y sin
una partición en la cláusula definido el más crea lo que es una sola
partición de todas estas filas. Como se puede ver aquí tenemos un select
ID de cliente fecha del pedido total a pagar, vamos a resumir, obtenemos agregando
la función de suma, total a pagar, crear un total prevista para ese cliente en particular.
Entonces tenemos la partición por el ID de cliente. Ahí es donde
vamos a crear sobre este contenido. Como el total ... total a pagar
por el cliente y agarrar esta información del encabezado sales.salesorder
y verá el ID de cliente 1100. Fecha Orden 1ro agosto, 2007.
Yo estaba tratando de leer la otra manera.
Tiene total a pagar de 37.56. Con un total a pagar por el cliente es 91.15.
Si nos fijamos en que hay tres filas aquí por ID de cliente 1100.
Si nos fijamos en total a pagar era 37.56. A continuación, 25.87 y 27.70
y si se agrega para arriba verá esos tres valores vendrán
muy cerca de ese 91.15.1341
si quieres bajar a las monedas de un centavo nano o lo que sea que
podría estar en el lado derecho de dicho punto decimal. Nótese que
tener la fecha de la orden en el que sólo están exhibiendo el año.
Nosotros no mostramos el actual, el tiempo asociado con eso.
Así que este es un ejemplo de que podemos recuperar información acerca
de un cliente en particular en diferentes órdenes, lo que la fecha de vencimiento,
de lo la cantidad se debió a cada pedido y oh, por cierto, lo que es
el cliente me debe como un total para ese fin. Así que teníamos para
that particular customer. Not specific to that order but for
the different orders that they've submitted to us. This would
be a cool way for us to find out if anyone's kind of got this
outstanding or ginormous amount of money that's due to us, we
can actually sort this and set this up so we can see who owes
us the most money so we know who to send our accounts receivable
people afterwards. How do we use this, create a windows function
applied to a window or set of rows, as we can saw it can include
ranking and distribution offset function that we introduced earlier on.
These are similar to grouped aggregate functions such as your
sum and your min, your max.
They're applied to windows defined by the over clause. The O-V-E-R,
upper case, we can recognize that when we're working with windows functions.
And support partitioning, ordering and framing of content in
the windows world. Now, the ranking functions that are available
to us, we have rank, dense rank, row number and end title.
The rank returns a rank of each row and it may include ties and
it may include gaps.
The dense rank returns the rank of each row, but this also may
include ties but it will not include gaps. If there's any gaps
in the content. The row number returns unique sequential number
within that partition based on where it is in that current order.
And the tile distributes rows in ordered partition and this returns
a number of the group to which that row belongs to. So I can
kind of figure out how they're categorized and where these rows
belong to.
The windows offset function, I believe we looked at this earlier.
This actually looks at the lag, return an expression from the
previous row and it's defined in the offset from the current row.
The lead, again, returns expression from the lighter row instead
of a previous row. First value, last value, pretty self-explanatory
returns a first value in the current windows frame or returns
the last value in the current windows frame.
>> Let me go ahead and demo this a little bit. Because like I
mentioned earlier, this is one of these things where you need
to get into a Zen place and then you'll basically be happy.
This is one of these super use of functions.
>> After this demo I'm going to be happy for life, I'll be in
Xen, I'll be there forever.
>> I'm not sure about forever.
>> At least for the rest of this module.
>> And you still use Fahrenheit. So I'm not sure.
>> Okay.
>> Let's go ahead and have a look. So I've just created a table
I call transactions, because banking kind of transactions makes
a fairly useful example.
So in this table, and I just stole some columns from the customers
or from the save order and details and pretend they're transactions.
So I apparently have account number, account ID, transaction
ID, transaction date and how much money they use in this transaction.
So let's just start by looking at one account number. So where
account ID equals this one.
And let's say what I now want to calculate, which is a very common
thing, it was very problematic before SQL Server 2012, especially
with the performance, okay I have all of these transactions,
but what is the current balance of the account? Right? Per a
given row. So let's say we have this query now.
And I can start by just using this aggregate, it's a sum I want,
some over amount. And we know we just can't do this because we
need to group by but I want to show the details. I want to show
at this particular moment in time this transaction happened and
the balance after the transaction is the following. So we'll
start by just doing over partition by account ID as current balance.
Or let's just call it final balance. So this will give me is
the sum across the whole account, right.
So now you can see the balance of this account is apparently
422,000 whatever pirate currency we're using here.
And then what I can do now is, okay, that's fine that's the end
balance, right. If I tell it the server instead to say over per
account because I want this per account...
do this so it makes it a bit easier to read... I want to say
give me the balance up until the current transaction. And what
that means is I need an order in here. Order doesn't matter
when you group. Logically. But it does matter when you want
to do cumulative thing. So here I'll say, well, order this by,
sorry not order date, transaction date. And since transaction
date isn't unique for me to be sure that this makes sense, I'll
include transaction ID in there.
And then I'll also use the same order by in the query. So I'll
do this so we're sure we get the results in the same order.
And it's important to note that
if you put an order by clause here, you may get the result in
this order but that's just by accident.
So if you want to be sure to get the results in a certain order,
you have to put an order by at the end of the query. And the
very common bug you see in applications is like you even saw
me do earlier, or even saw me, but I also did that.
>> You did that, I didn't see it.
>> So often it's important that the order by is unique.
That's why I added this transaction ID in there. Let's go ahead
and run this query.
And now you can see that the balance is... I called that one
final balance. Let's call that one current balance. Just to
be clear.
Now you can see how the current balance is increasing as we go
because it's the sum of the current row and all rows preceding that.
And you may argue and say well does it do that it says order by.
Doesn't really make sense. That's the part of the ANSI specification
of the language if you say order by it's implicit you're using
a framing clause to say only include certain amount of rows.
So what's the
syntax for this. Can you show the PowerPoint slide again?
>> I certainly can.
Which one are we looking for?
>> Now I remember.
Rows between
current row...
rows unbounded
preceding and rows... we're seeing between unbounded preceding
and current row I think something like that. That makes sense. Okay.
Okay. So this is what this actually means implicitly. It is
values between current row and/or unbounded preceding and current row.
But you can read up a bit on the differences. But basically
now it makes more sense. Sort for each account sort the result
like this and now for this particular row include everything
from the beginning of the partition or the frame, i.e., for this
account, for the beginning of the transaction for the account,
up until this row.
And you can also say starting at this row between this row and
unbounded following, if you want to go forward instead.
But this is obviously super, super useful if you want to do calculations
like this. You can imagine just by looking at the result set
this is fairly common, the running total.
And this is super super efficient the way we implemented it.
The other thing that's very interesting is lag and lead. So I'll
show just a quick example of that.
So let's just say we have the production product table
and let's actually continue with this set since we have an example running.
So let's say okay this is all nice. But I want to see what is
the difference between the current transaction and the previous one.
Which is a very common thing that you want to say what's the
difference between this and the next row in the set or the previous
row in the set or the five rows back or whatever. This very
common calculation.
So what I can just say is okay please grab me lag. I want to
go backwards in the set.
And I want to grab the amount column and this is an expression,
the amount plus something whatever, amount. And default is to
go one step back. I want to go one back, and if there is no row
preceding what would I like to get. If there's no row preceding
I'll get null back. Then I say please give me zero instead.
Lag, obviously lag is the same thing. It requires an order.
So we say this is over for the account, within this account step
back, and give me based on the same order by clause. So order
by transaction date. Transaction ID. Now it knows go one step
back and grab me the previous amount. So we can just see
this query. Now we can see okay this is the previous amount we
see there's no one before. That's zero. You can see how these
match up as we go down.
Obviously I can say what is the difference now between amount
and previous amount. This amount is it bigger smaller than the
previous one.
And now we can see well this is obviously bigger than...
there were no previous one, this one is this much bigger and
this one this much smaller and so on.
And this is just kind of tickling your interest. But you can
imagine you can do a lot with these calculations. And it may
seem a bit intimidating if you're looking at it for the first time.
But this is really a recommendation, if there's anything that's
useful, it is this. Lots of calculations can be done.
It's actually... it's not very hard once you get to know it,
which is obviously common. English is not hard if you know it.
British is not hard if you know it. If you're interested in
SQL you should spend some time on windows functions and playing
around with it.
>> What's the calculation from Fahrenheit to Celsius, this is
easy compared to that, isn't it?
>> That's why who in the world uses Fahrenheit.
>> Canada.
>> I thought it was Celsius. We all know Celsius is Swedish, just
to be clear here.
>> That was good. Let's move into grouping sets. We'll talk about
grouping sets. Here we'll talk about pivoting. Pivoting is kind
of unique in the sense that what we do is we take the rows...
so we've got this category, quantity and order here that we have here.
And then under category we've got different items, different
products and quantity and good order year, excuse me. Now what
we can do is spin those and rotate the column so under category
we maintain, in this case, the beverages, now we've created a
column for each of the years that are available for beverages.
So this is called a pivoted table. We create distinct values
from a single column and we set up the headings for other columns.
And these headings can include or information in these columns
can include aggregation. So this is a pivoted table here.
So sample query of this would be select category. These are
years 2006, seven and eight. And you have a from statement, select
category, quantity and order year.
From sales category, quantity year, as D. And then we pivot
and we're going to sum the quantity for the order year in 2006,
seven and eight. So the grouping is the category as you can see here.
The aggregation is the sum quantity that we'll see, that we've seen.
And the spreading is how do we want to separate this out?
2006, seven, eight or by year. And we set it up, we give it a
name, as PBT. That way we can see that.
When we've done that, let me actually go back so you can see
what it's like here. So that's what this brings out for us, that query.
It gives us this information that was normally over here.
Dairy products 2006, and you'll see under 2006 there's a total
of 2,086. Here we see five. It's doing a calculation for us.
It's rotating the content that was in this table into this pivot
table and then storing that information in there using this type
of command. So the grouping determines the elements that get
populated in the result set. The spreading provides the distinct
value that we're going to use and then the aggregated function
in this case here is the sum that we're going to use. So we
get a sum instead of individual items that we have set up here.
I'm going the wrong way here. We've got to go back the other way.
Here we are. Here's another example of this. Select vendor ID.
And we're going to set this up 250 as employee one, 251 is employee two.
All the way through employee five. And then from, then we're
going to do a select statement from the purchase order ID with
these items, employee ID, vendor ID. We're going to grab this
information from the purchase order header information which
we're going to retitle or as our alias has P. And we're going
to say we want to pivot. Create a pivot. We'll count the purchase
order ID for the employee that's in these, in this table, columns
250, 51, 56, 57 and 60.
And as pivot. And order by pivot or PVAT.vendor.ID.
What we'll do is you see order by, you'll see these are 1492,
94 and 96. And for each employee employee, one, two, three, four,
five, which are associated with employees, 250, 51, 56, 57, 60.
This is the vendor ID or information associated with that.
>> This all sounds super simple.
>> Sounds super simple.
>> This is one of these clauses that always gets me confused myself.
But it's actually following the ANSI SQL standard. It's worth
noting that pivot and unpivot
or actually pivot especially is not super heavily used just because
it's very common that you do this type of pivoting in whatever
reporting type of application you're using, Excel or porting
services or you're building your own, rather than doing it directly
in the SQL statement. There are definitely reasons to go and
use this, but it's worth noting that typically you do this type
of pivoting up in the application layer.
>> You mentioned the unpivot. We won't get into this, but here's
an example of this so you'll have it. It's create a table.
This actually does the opposite. Unpivots. Insert values here
and then you generate something... and this is, down here I
just squeezed in just what the output would look like, vendor
ID one, employee one and the orders forms, kind of doing the reverse.
>> This is actually more interesting in a sense, or more common,
I'd say, because it's fairly common that you see just table structures
where it's basically not normalized in a reasonable way. So the
table actually includes whatever year and then employee one,
two, three, four, and you want to write a query on top of that.
Then you can use unpivot to actually get it into a more normalized
form and then you can query on top of the output of the unpivot.
Because obviously unpivot can be part of a common table expression
derived table view, et cetera. Unpivot is probably more common
that you would use than pivot in regular queries.
>> Especially in normalized data. Normalized data easier to get
that content out and slice and dice it the way you wanted to,
being it wasn't populated correctly in the first place.
Writing grouping sets.
Build on your T SQL group by clause and allows us to create multiple
groupings, and alternative uses, the union all which was demonstrated
earlier on. But this is an example, I don't know if I have an
example in here. I do. We do a select territory ID, customer ID.
Do an aggregate function of sum as total amount due and then
from the sales order table, header table excuse me we'll group
by then we'll use grouping sets. We'll have a group set of territory
ID and customer ID.
What I did is when I created this, there were several hundred
of rows and I took this information from towards the bottom because
a bunch of territory IDs were blank or null so down towards the
bottom where we've got some valid information you see the territory
IDs are grouped now and then we'll have the total amount for
each of the territories.
So this was a grouping set here provides this information per
customer ID. For each of the customer IDs here.
>> We go into a demo in a few slides and look a little more into
the details of this.
>> Cubes and roll-up or cube and roll-up. Provides shortcut for
defining these group sets.
Creates a cube, creates all possible combination of grouping sets.
In this case here we're doing a select territory ID and customer ID.
Again sum for total due and we're going to ping the sales order
header table. We're going to group by and throw the word cube
in there. Again territory ID, customer ID and we'll order it
by territory ID and customer ID. The roll-up is very similar
in the sense that it provides a shortcut for defining the group sets.
Creates combinations of assuming input columns from a hierarchy.
So this is more of a hierarchical approach than a cubing, when
we use the cube process, I should say. So we've got a couple
of these options that are available to us for summarizing our
data instead of looking at details of information giving us a
summary of data.
Working with pivot cube and roll-up. I say you may not want
to work with a pivot so much but whatever you feel like demoing.
>> I think we've just basically shown just a little bit of what's
going on here. And it's actually just simpler than what you would imagine.
So let's just say we want to say, we want to get total sales
by customer and territory, right? So we have customer ID, territory
ID, from sales customer.
And then I'll go ahead and just join this with
sales order header
and then go and join it with
sales order detail.
So there we go. We have the kind of the join. And let's just
say I want a total sales. So I want the sum of
sales order detail. I think it's unit or line total, I think,
we even have there.
As total sales.
And need to go in group by these two columns. Okay. So that's great.
I get now the total sales for this territory and this customer
and if you scroll down they're different customers.
And scroll down more, we get total sales for customers in different territories.
And if it happens to be a customer that are in multiple territories,
then which can't happen per the schema, right, but then you will
see obviously there. This is all
great but it's likely someone will ask the question, well, what
is the total sales for the customer independent of territory
or for the territory independent of the customer. And then without
these grouping sets and whatnot, what you would typically do
is you would add another query, separately,
and just have the sum there. Let's say we want the total sales.
And that would be this.
And then you say well I want this in one result set and I go
and put these both together, right? And I'll just say order by
customer ID in the result set.
Now, this won't work since I have three columns up here and one
column down here. I'll just say, well, this returns null for
these two columns and now the result sets match and I can put
them together.
But obviously there's a lot of writing that goes on here in order
to get this result set. And as we all know the more code you
write, the more bugs you will put in there, right? So less code
equals less bugs.
>> That's definitely true.
>> So if I instead do this, I'll just say, well, I want to group
by, and I want to create grouping sets.
So now I can say not just this is the final and only. I can
say, well, I want one set is please group by customer and territory
ID as a combination. This is exactly just running this exactly
the same as the first query.
Let's add the order by as well.
But now I can add other sets that interest me. So if I want
this total that I just showed. We can just add an empty set here,
which means that's the total across all the customers and all territories.
Now I have the same as the previous query but clearly less writing.
>> Less code, definitely.
>> Now I can go and say, well, I'm interested in actually the
total for the territories independent of customers as well.
So now I'm getting
first this is the total sales roll-up and then per territory
what's the sale, and then I get per customer.
So I can go with... I'm sorry... with grouping sets and basically
add the groupings that I'm interested in using.
Another thing that's interesting to note here is how do you know
if the null value returned is actually because there is a null
value that you are grouping together, or it's a null value generated
by these grouping sets. See the difference like here I just happen
to know that there is no customer with customer 80 null and no
territory ID null so I know this is the aggregate. But it could
also be the sum of all sales for customer null territory ID null.
So there's a function called grouping that you can use to find
out with a case expression if grouping for a column returns one,
that means it was a generated null because of the grouping.
And if it returns zero it means an actual real null value if
it happens to be null. So that's interesting you can then differentiate
between null values that you're actually grouping over versus
null values being generated.
>> Very nice. I like the fact there's less code, less chance of
undocumented feature. I versus to use that versus a bug.
Undocumented feature that we don't introduce that instead.
So that's good to have that.
So what we looked at here is working with sets, the interaction
between sets of data results can be combined, operated against.
Order by is not allowed in the input queries. Set operators
include the union, the intersection or the intersect and the
except and the apply. We have examples of the union, the union
all, intercept and except, and using they're using the Adventures
Works database. These will work within the Adventures Works database.
A couple of people chatted in and asked where do I get that,
a couple of people asked first off where do I get a free version
of SQL Server. So there's a SQL Server Express version you can
download and install. Then you can install the Adventure Works.
So what you're seeing here you want to dabble with, you've got
the ability to dabble without writing a big check. SQL Express version.
Actual limitation, we couldn't bring it out in a real world production,
big environment. But then you can use some of these queries you're
seeing and you can set up the Adventure Works database so that
way you can execute these queries against that database.
We also introduced some windows function, the rank, dense rank,
the row number, the end tile. And we set a cool demo in the lag
and some other offset functions like the first value and the
last value that we looked at. Pivoting, probably not something
you want to spend a lot of time or lose any sleep over.
But the nonpivoting for unnormalized data would be beneficial
for you. Grouping set was really helpful and then we had the
cube and the roll-up that are available for us for grouping sets
of content. So that's going to wrap up this section here.
So what we'll do at this point is we're going to take a ten-minute break.
We're going to get prepared for our next section in Module 6
is coming up. So we'll ask you to step back, take a breather,
take a ten-minute break and we'll be back with you shortly.